Inventory of the Student Papers About Middletown Collection, 1972 - 2012
Student Papers About Middletown Collection, 1972 - 2012
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-133
2.5
5
Since 1972, student papers written on historical Middletown-area topics have been donated to Special Collections & Archives.
The Student Papers About Middletown Collection featuers graduate and undergraduate papers about the history of Middletown, Connecticut and the surrounding area. Topics include politics, labor, commerce, ethnic and racial groups, women's history, and leisure.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Received from faculty and students, 1972-2012.
Historical Note
Wesleyan University has offered a number of courses which discuss Middletown, Connecticut and its history. Since 1972, student papers written on historical Middletown-area topics have been donated to Special Collections & Archives.
Collection Overview
The Student Papers About Middletown Collection featuers graduate and undergraduate papers about the history of Middletown, Connecticut and the surrounding area. Topics include politics, labor, commerce, ethnic and racial groups, women's history, and leisure.
Collection Arrangement
The papers are arranged in alphabetical order by author's last name.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --Students.; Middletown (Conn.) --Commerce.; Middletown (Conn.) --History.; Middletown (Conn.) --Politics and government.; Middletown (Conn.) --Social conditions.; Middletown (Conn.) --Emigration and immigration.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Author unknown, The Rich in the City of Middletown in 1860, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    View pdf in WesScholar.
  - Albrecht, Anthony, Like a Puzzle With All of its Pieces, Xavier is Complete With Community Help, circa 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Allen, Elizabeth K., Connecticut Valley Hospital, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barr, Leslie, Music and Dance in Middletown in the Late 18th and Early 19th Century, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barr, Leslie, Twas Not a Time for New England to Dance [Music and Dance in Early Middletown], 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barry, John, The Starr Family of Middletown, Ct.: A Study in Social Mobility and Social Experience, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Belkin, Erica, The Colonization Societies: Middletown's Forgotten Movement, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bennion, Craig and Mary Francis White, Middletown Newspapers of the Late 19th Century, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Berlew, Christopher, Middletown and the Civil War: Who Prospered? 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Blake, Casey, Irish Immigrants in Middletown, Connecticut, 1830-1860, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Borders, Craig, A Method of Ascertaining the Identity of Small- and Medium-size Farmers, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Breidenbach, Paul, Americanization of Polish and Italian Immigrants in Middletown, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bruce, Phyllis, Minds, Minstrels, and Melpomene at McDonough, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bruce, Phyllis Ruth, The Career of the Continental Vocalists and the Life of its Co-Founder, William Dwight Franklin, Middletown, Ct. Resident, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Campbell, John and Jessica Lacy, A Social Analysis of Blacks in Middletown, 1850-1880, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Carrell, Kimberley W., Celebration of Christmas and the 4th of July, Middletown, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Center, Claudia, Urban Renewal and Citizens Groups in Middletown, Connecticut, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chandler, Julia Anne, Services and Societies in First Church of Christ, Middletown, 1870-1890, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Conescu, Rachel, The Lower Washington Street Community: An Unfinished Portrait, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cruse, Katherine, William Brenton Hall: a Biography, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cuckow, Elizabeth, A Ripple of Disorder: The IWW, Immigrants, and Upheaval in the New England Textile Industry, 1912, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Cunningham, Jan, The Development of American Public Education and the Midletown Experience, 1870-1920, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cunningham, Jan, The Millers of Middlefield: a Case Study in American Social History, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cunningham, Jan, The Family System in Transition: Wealth and Inheritance Practice in Middlefield, 1750-1850, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - D'Arienzo, Daria, Elizabeth Bigelow, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - D'Arienzo, Daria, Hartford's Italians, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dickman, Howard, The Middletown Manufacturing Company, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Druker, Michele, Weighed, Counted and Measured: Manufacturing in Middletown, 1860-1880, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Early, Gerry, The Second Great Awakening in Middletown: a Paradox of Progress, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Edelstein, Ken, A Survey of Middletown Nespapers in th 1820s, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Effron, Lucy, Small Retail Businesses in Middletown, 1870-1900, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Farrell, Sheila Wrang and Annette DiMauro Grimaldi, A Study in Depth of Italian Wedding Photos of Middletown Families, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fisher, Margaret, Immigrant Success: What Is It, and How Does One Achieve It? 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Francis, Abbey, Sex at Wesleyan: From the 1930s to the 1960s, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Frentz, Susan M., Middletown, Connecticut, 1820: Investigations and Discoveries of Its Women and Its Social Order, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Frentz, Susan M., Urbanization and the Female-headed Household, Middletown, Connecticut, 1790-1850, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Friedman, Howard, The Progressive Experience in Middletown, 1900-1920, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fuller, Elaine Xenelis, From the Greek-American Fruit and Candy Company, 1901 to the Middlesex Fruitery, 1981: The Assimilation of a Greek-American Family, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Furrer, Tom, The Rise and Decline of Welfare Capitalism and the Emergence of a Union in Ivoryton, Connecticut, 1900-1941, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gaebe, John, The Great Depression and Its Impact on the City of Middletown, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Garin, Nickolas Atteraas, Policing a New Middletown: Updating the Force at the Turn of the 20th Century, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Giardina, James A., Swedish Immigration to Cromwell, Connecticut, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Golec, Josephine Barry, The Founding of the Middlesex Hospital, 1895-1905, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gray, Brenda Ellen, The Relationship Between Social History and Historical Archaeology: The Mercantile Community of Middletown, Connecticut, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Gross, R. Barrett and David Engstrom, The Development of Industry in Middletown, Connecticut: With An Emphasis on the Post Civil War Economic Boom, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Grucan, Sally P., The Printer-Publishers of the Middlesex Gazette from 1785 to 1820: an Examination of their Position in the Middletown Community, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hanley, Ben, The Irish in Middletown: The Pre Famine Generations, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Head, Patricia, The Social Condition of Women in Early Nineteenth Century Middletown and America, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Hechtkopf, Quinn, Two Years of Protest: Divestment at Wesleyan University, 1988-1990, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Helfer, Rachel, Voluntary Associations and the Y.M.C.A. in Middletown, 1885-1911, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hennigan, Anne F., Railroads and Economic Development in Middletown, 1865-1880, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hetorilla, Ann, Marriage and the Chauncey Name, circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hobby, Matt, Blacks in Middletown Around the 1790s: a summary of information obtained primarily from land records, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hollister, Timothy S., A Prosopographical Study of State Legislators from Middletown, 1860-1910, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Houseley, Kathleen, 'Who Can Blot Out the North Star?' The Bemans -- Four Generations of Black Abolitionists, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Houston, John and Alex Kotlowitz, Class Conflict in Middletown: the Remington-Rand Strike of 1936, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - James, Charles, Middletown: The Promised Land? 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Joachim, Alan, The Interrelationships of the Merchant Careers of Five Alsops and Economic Changes, 1750-1878, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Klingher, Michael, The Connecticut State Hospital for the Insane, 1866-1920 and the Transformation of Modern America, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Kovach, Steven, The Beginning of Middletown's Transition into a Factory Town: The Year 1900, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Krakaur, Keith Douglas, The Ideology of Mobility: a Study of Irish Economic and Group Assimilation in Late Nineteenth Century Middletown, Connecticut, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lansky, Madeleine, A Comparative Study of the Ethnic Identity of Italian-Americans in Middletown, Connecticut Before and After World War II, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Laurent, Bret, Lumber, Shipbuilding and the Early Connecticut River Trade, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Loether, J. Paul, A Preliminary Study of the Brownstone Quarrying Industry in the Town of Portland, Connecticut, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Loether, J. Paul, Middletown, Connecticut: Ethnic Composition and Residential Distribution, 1850-1880, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Mac Lean, Diane, Quiltmaking in Connecticut, 1750-1850, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Masback, Becca, Middletown, Connecticut: Summer of 1969, Civil Disturbances and Community Relations in an American City, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Meranze, M., The Social Characteristics of the Middletown Political Elite, 1900-1920, circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Milano, Marche, The Famine Generation: the Middletown Irish in the 1850s, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Morales, Jawn, George Aylward as Middletown Police Chief, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Moriarty, Patrick, The 1940 Election in Middletown, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Morton, Peg, The Hall Family: a Study in the Patriarchal System, 1650-1850, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Mothes, Nancy, A Survey of Employment Opportunities Offered in Middletown Newspapers, 1850-1890: Sampling from Newspapers at Five Year Intervals During the First Week of Each Quarter, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Myrow, Susan, Journalism of Middletown, Connecticut Between 1870-1920, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Nasta, Jesse, Local Relief in Middletown During the Great Depression, 1930-1933, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Neuman, Patricia, Working Mens' Societies in Middletown Connecticut: the Franklin Society of 1829-1931 and the Mechanics Society of 1832-1836, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Norment, Katie, Middletown Artisans, 1810, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Norwood, Dael, A Constant and Formidable Foe: Josual Stow and the Fight for Religious Freedom in Connecticut, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Nyman, Brenda and Mark Swartz, Crime in Middletown and Middlesex County in 1880-1910, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - O'Connell, Brendan, From Labor Leader to Police Chief: A Biography of Charles Anderson, 1912-1936, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Odim, Carlton, The Black Population of Middletown, 1790-1850, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Ostlund, Rachel, Revolutions in Agriculture in Middlesex County, Connecticut During the Mid-19th Century, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Paffrath, Ronald A., Port of Call: An Examination of Aspects of Maritime Commerce in Middletown, Connecticut During the Period 1790 Through 1820, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pena, Ted, The Short and Obscure Historical Geography of Maromas, circa 1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Peretz, Steven, A Demographic Profile of Early 19th Century Middletown, Connecticut: a Statistical Analysis, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Perlstein, Daniel, The House that Isaac [Warner] Built, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Pitterman, Bernard, A Speculative Study of the Middlesex Theatre, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Platt, Julie, Title IX and College Athletics: A Case Study of Wesleyan University and Equality, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Porteus, Gail Linskey, A Profile of Two Irish Families: the Larkins and the Linskeys, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Poss, Robert M., Middletown Research: The Care of the Poor, 1750-1790, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Post, Stephen E., The Courageous Captain and the Rise and Fall of Middletown's Military Academy, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Potter, Lucy, Yellow Fever in Middle Haddam, 1796, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Potts, Betsy H., 'A Flourishing College Will... Build Up a Town:' the Twelve Local Trustees of Wesleyan University, 1830-1840, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Riether, Charles, The 1983 Mayoral Election: Tradition Trumps Change, circa 1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Riklin, Matthew, The Evolution of Food Retailing in the 20th Century, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Rose, Max, The 1969 Middletown Election: A Case Study for the Importance of Majority Party Unity circa 2008 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Savas, Stephanie, The War That Came Home: The Individuals That Personalized the 1918 Influenza Epidemic in Middletown, Connecticut, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Schneider, Judith, The Regulations of the Garden Are Such as to Prevent All Improper Conduct and Exclude Everything that Might Offend the Chastest Ear: Amusements and Leisure Time Activities in Middletown, 1828-1838, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Schorr, Brian, A Narrative History of Prohibition in Middletown, Connecticut, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Schulz, Carol D., Joshua Stow: a Nineteenth Century Rebel, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Shaner, Laurie, Trials and Triumphs: True Stories of Slavery in Connecticut, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Shea, Jonathan, The Polish Community of New Britain, 1900-1925, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sherrow, Doris, The Corner of Main and Court ... A Turning Point, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sherrow, Doris, Jews in Portland--The Eastern Tinware Community, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sherrow, Doris, Murder in Middletown: Lower Class Life in 1815, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sonnenblick, Charlotte, Printers, Publishers and Booksellers in Middletown, Connecticut: the Demise of the Independent Craftsman, 1800-1850, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Staley, Ellen, The Connecticut Industrial School for Girls, 1870-1920: Legal Assumptions and Social Class Expectations, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sternberg, Corinne, Joshua Stow: Local Scapegoat, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Svonkin, Stuart, The Creation of a Pluralistic Religious Orientation: The Integration of Jews and Judiasm at Wesleyan University, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Sweeney, Bob, Middletown Temperance, 1816-1846, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Tarallo, Frank J., A Biography of Richard Alsop the 3rd of Middletown, Connecticut, born 1789, died May 29, 1842, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Terzini, Carol, The Frothingham House, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Tillinghast, Joel, [Wesleyan History], circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Torczon, Virginia, The Professionalization of Middletown's Physicians, 1868-1918, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Tucker, William, Middletown and Mental Illness in the Aftermath of Deinstitutionalization, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Vanacore, Brad M., The Brownstone Quarries of Portland Connecticut: Their Contribution to the Development of the United States, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Veroff, Daniel, Middletown's Blacks, 1800-1840, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Vinci, Leon F., A Middletown-American in Show Business: Tony Pastor, 1909-1969, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - White, Mary Francis, Introduction to 'The Producers' of Middletown, and a Major Product--the Newspapers, 1820-1833, circa 1978 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Wilder, Barry, Middletown Masons, 1796-1826: a Study of the Role Played by a Voluntary Organization in a Traditional Community Experiencing Rapid Dissolution, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Wilder, Barry, Different Shades of Green: a Study of Irish-American Institutions in Middletown, Connecticut, 1880-1915, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Wrubel, Regina, The Mortimer Cemetery in Middletown's Transition, 1815, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 22)